A Guide to the Helen Wolfe Evans Papers, 1860-2002
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Helen Wolfe Evans Papers, 1860-2002
Library of Virginia
42286
1.05 cu. ft. and 1 oversize folder.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Helen Wolfe Evans, Raleigh, North Carolina, 31 October 2005.
Biographical/Historical Information
Helen Wolfe Evans (1935- ) was born Helen Baldwin Wolfe on 9 February 1935 in Richmond, Virginia, the daughter of Helen Perkins Hughes Wolfe (1897-1992) and Thomas Kennerly Wolfe (1892-1972). Her elder brother is the novelist Tom Wolfe (1930- ). On 21 August 1957, she married Murphy Evans (1932- ) in Richmond. The couple, which eventually relocated to North Carolina, had four children: Helen Hughes Evans, Virginia Borden Evans, David Murphy Evans, and Thomas Kennerly Wolfe Evans. In 1989, Helen Wolfe Evans earned a Master of Arts in Liberal Studies degree from Duke University. Much of her research there focused on Ella Graham Agnew (1871-1958), younger sister of Evans's maternal grandmother, Martha "Mattie" Agnew Hughes (1860-1934).
Scope and Content
Papers, 1860-2002, include correspondence, newspaper clippings, and legal documents gathered by Helen Wolfe Evans (1935- ) while researching the life of her great-aunt Ella Graham Agnew (1871-1958), an educator, administrator, and pioneer of the home demonstration movement. Files deal with various aspects of Agnew's life and legacy, including family members, friends, and business associates; the town of Burkeville, Virginia, where she spent her childhood; her service as a teacher and seminary principal in South Africa from 1895-1900; her place in and the general history of home demonstration work; organizations and agencies with which she was involved, including the Young Women's Christian Association and the Works Progress Administration; and honors such as buildings named after her, an honorary doctorate from the College of William and Mary, and a highway marker. Also included are a genealogy of the Agnew, Hughes, and related families; a transcript of a 1988 interview by Evans of her mother, Helen Hughes Wolfe; and two papers, 1988 and 1989, written on Agnew by Evans while a graduate student at Duke University.
Arrangement
File groupings and labels assigned by the donor have been maintained for the most part, and are arranged alphabetically.
Contents List
- Papers, 1860-2002 (Box 1-3)
  Papers, 1860-2002, include correspondence, newspaper clippings, and legal documents gathered by Helen Wolfe Evans (1935- ) while researching the life of her great-aunt Ella Graham Agnew (1871-1958), an educator, administrator, and pioneer of the home demonstration movement. Files deal with various aspects of Agnew's life and legacy, including family members, friends, and business associates; the town of Burkeville, Virginia, where she spent her childhood; her service as a teacher and seminary principal in South Africa from 1895-1900; her place in and the general history of home demonstration work; organizations and agencies with which she was involved, including the Young Women's Christian Association and the Works Progress Administration; and honors such as buildings named after her, an honorary doctorate from the College of William and Mary, and a highway marker. Also included are a genealogy of the Agnew, Hughes, and related families; a transcript of a 1988 interview by Evans of her mother, Helen Hughes Wolfe; and two papers, 1988 and 1989, written on Agnew by Evans while a graduate student at Duke University.
  Arrangement
  alphabetical by folder title.
  - Agnew Association newsletter (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Agnew--Assorted notes (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Agnew coat of arms (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Agnew-Hughes and others, genealogy (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Alexander Forward (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Aunt Meda, Aunt Ellen, Jas. Fowlkes, Perkins Agnew (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Boys' work--T.O. Sandy--Farm demonstration (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Burkeville Cemetery (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Burkeville--family (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Burkeville--History, "Great Road," Jennings Ordinary (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Commission on Interracial Cooperation (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Confederate Home (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Craft exhibit (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Defense nutrition work, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Dictionary of Virginia Biography, M. Swain (Box 1, Folder 15-16)
  - Duke paper I (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Duke paper II (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Ella Graham Agnew--Associates (Box 1, Folder 19-20)
  - Ella Graham Agnew--Biographical sketches (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Ella Graham Agnew--Death certificate (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Ella Graham Agnew portrait, VPI (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Ella Graham Agnew and Winston Churchill (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Ella Graham Agnew--1920's (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - George Melton--Progressives (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Grove Avenue (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Hampton archives (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Her Story--Home Demonstration, and other histories (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Highway marker (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Home demonstration clippings (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Home demonstration/Home economics resources (Box 2, Folder 32-38)
  - Home demonstration work (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Home extension pay, Black and White (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - James Anderson Agnew (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - James Perkins Agnew (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Kathleen Hilton paper (on EGA) (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Land tract drawing, signed "Agnew," n.d. (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Martha Meade Perkins (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - McLean family (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Naming, second building (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Negro work (salaries compared to White) (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Nottoway Co. houses, Iverness (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Nottoway Co. wills, Agnew-McLean (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Obituaries--Ella Graham Agnew and Mattie Agnew Hughes (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Olive Schreiner (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Rhea Scott case (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Samuel McLean (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - South Africa (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - South Africa--Archives (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Southern Planter (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Transcription, taped interview of Helen Hughes Wolfe, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Virginia Federation of Business and Professional Women's Clubs (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Virginia Historical Society--"Nottoway Stuff" (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Virginia Tech--Agnew resources (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - William and Mary degree (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - William Bingay Agnew (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - Woman's Work Today, 1917, article by EGA (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - Works Progress Administration (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - Works Progress Administration--Looking back (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - Works Progress Administration--Resources (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - YWCA (Box 3, Folder 68)